[
    {
        "question": "He hæfde gefeormod (<em>fot</em>) #### ond handa - He had devoured feet and hands",
        "correctAnswer": "fet",
        "explanation":"Here 'fot' is in the accusative and plural so the root-vowel changes from 'o' to 'e' to become 'fet'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wiþ banece genim tuning wyrt beolone wealwyrt ealde grut ond eced, heorotes smera oþþe gate oþþe (<em>gos</em>) ####, meng tosomne lege þonneon - For bone ache, take white veratrum, dwarf elder, spent malt, and vinegar, hart’s fat or goat’s or goose’s, mix together, then apply",
        "correctAnswer": "gose",
        "explanation":"Here 'gos' is in the genitive and singular so it gains the 'e' ending to become 'gose'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "goses",
                "explanation": "While 'gos' is in the genitive and singular, it is a feminine noun, and so takes the feminine 'e' ending, not the masculine 'es' ending, to become 'gose'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif wyrm ete þa (<em>toð</em>) #### genim ofer geare holen rinde ond eoforþrotan moran wel on swa hatumhafa on muþe swa hat swa þu hatost mæge - If a worm eats the teeth take holly bark more than a year old and the root of stemless carline thistle, boil in such hot water, hold in the mouth as hot as you can",
        "correctAnswer": "teð",
        "explanation":"Here 'toð' is in the accusative and plural so the root-vowel changes from 'o' to 'e' to become 'teð'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "We Us gegadrian to his halgan gelaðunge, þæt ure naman beon awritene on lifes (<em>boc</em>) #### mid his gecorenum - We gather us to his holy congregation that our names may be written in the book of life with his chosen",
        "correctAnswer": "bec",
        "explanation":"Here 'boc' is in the dative and singular so the root-vowel changes from 'o' to 'e' to become 'bec'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He his wæs (<em>freond</em>) #### gefylled - He was deprived of his friends",
        "correctAnswer": "freonda",
        "explanation":"Here 'freond' is in the genitive and plural so it gains the 'a' ending to become 'freonda'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þis geat ne bið nanum (<em>mann</em>) #### geopenod, ac se Hlaford ana færð inn þurh þæt geat - This gate shall be opened to no man, for the Lord only will go in by that gate",
        "correctAnswer": "menn",
        "explanation":"Here 'mann' is in the dative and singular so the root-vowel changes from 'a' to 'e' to become 'menn'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic ne lufie (<em>mus</em>) #### ond flæa forðam ðe hie sind flesclicu nytenu nes men - I don't like mice and fleas because they are carnal creatures, not men",
        "correctAnswer": "mys",
        "explanation":"Here 'mus' is in the accusative and plural so the root-vowel changes from 'u' to 'y' to become 'mys'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif ðu gemete ðines (<em>feond</em>) #### oxan oððe assan, lad hine to him - If you meet your enemy's ox or donkey, you lead them back to him",
        "correctAnswer": "feondes",
        "explanation":"Here 'feond' is in the genitive and singular so it gains the 'es' ending to become 'feondes'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "feonde",
                "explanation": "While 'feond' is in the genitive and singular, it is a masculine noun, and so takes the masculine 'es' ending, not the feminine 'e' ending, to become 'feondes'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Wiþ (<em>lus</em>) #### acrind ond hwon wermod gecnua on ealu sele drincan - For lice, grind oak bark and a little wormwood in ale, give to drink",
        "correctAnswer": "lusum",
        "explanation":"Here 'lus' is in the dative and plural so it gains the 'um' ending to become 'lusum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðone æðeling on ðære (<em>burg</em>) #### metton, ðar se cyning ofslægen læg - They found the prince in the walled town where the king lay slain",
        "correctAnswer": "byrg",
        "explanation":"Here 'burg' is in the dative and singular so the root-vowel changes from 'u' to 'y' to become 'byrg'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wiþ ealcum heardum swile oððe geswelle gebeat hunan meng wiþ rysele oððe (<em>gate</em>) #### horn gebærned ond wiþ wætergemenged lege on - For every hard swelling and pustule beat horehound, mix with grease or burned goat’s horn mixed with water and apply",
        "correctAnswer": "gate",
        "explanation":"Here 'gat' is in the genitive and singular so it gains the 'e' ending to become 'gate'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic ðæt gehate ðæt ic heonon nelle fleon (<em>fot</em>) #### trym - I vow that I will not flee hence one footstep",
        "correctAnswer": "fotes",
        "explanation":"Here 'fot' is in the genitive and singular so it gains the 'es' ending to become 'fotes'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Feawa he awrat be his menniscnysse, forðam þe þa ðry oðre godspelleras genihtsumlice be þam heora (<em>boc</em>) #### setton - He wrote few things of his human nature, because the three other evangelists had composed their books abundantly concerning that.",
        "correctAnswer": "bec",
        "explanation":"Here 'boc' is in the accusative and plural so the root-vowel changes from 'o' to 'e' to become 'bec'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæt inwitspell Abraham sægde (<em>freond</em>) #### sinum - Abraham told that tale of woe to his friends",
        "correctAnswer": "freondum",
        "explanation":"Here 'freond' is in the dative and plural so it gains the 'um' ending to become 'freondum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se hundredman sende his (<em>freond</em>) #### to him - The centurion sent his friends to him",
        "correctAnswer": "friend",
        "explanation":"Here 'friend' is in the accusative and plural so the root-vowel changes from 'eo' to 'ie' to become 'friend'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Forðam ðe Crist is ealra hlaforda Hlaford, ægðer ge (<em>mann</em>) #### ge ealra gesceafta - For Christ is Lord of all lords, both of men and of all creatures",
        "correctAnswer": "manna",
        "explanation":"Here 'mann' is in the genitive and plural so it gains the 'a' ending to become 'manna'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif he us deadlicum (<em>mann</em>) #### ærist and þæt ece lif behete, hwa wolde þonne his behatum gelyfan? - If he to us mortal men had promised resurrection and life eternal, who would have believed in his promises?",
        "correctAnswer": "mannum",
        "explanation":"Here 'mann' is in the dative and plural so it gains the 'um' ending to become 'mannum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wiþ weartum, genim hundes micgean ond (<em>mus</em>) #### blod, meng tosomne, smire mid þa weartan ond hie gewitaþ sona aweg - For warts, take hound's urine and mouse's blood, mix together, anoint the warts with it and they will soon go away",
        "correctAnswer": "muse",
        "explanation":"Here 'mann' is in the genitive and singular so it gains the 'e' ending to become 'muse'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se (<em>feond</em>) #### his diorlingas duguþum stepte - The fiend decked his favourites with honours",
        "correctAnswer": "feond",
        "explanation":"Here 'feond' is the subject and singular so it takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    }
]